Finding Aid for Dept. of Internal Medicine (University of Michigan) publications 1948-2000
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Dept. of Internal Medicine (University of Michigan) publications 1948-2000, 1979-2000
University of Michigan. Dept. of Internal Medicine.
0.8 linear feet
Includes annual reports, brochures and pamphlets, bulletins, programs, and reports from the Dept. of Internal Medicine; in addition to brochures from subunits and related clinics such as the Division of Cardiology, the Division of Molecular and Human Genetics, and the Division of Nuclear Medicine.
0241 Bimu C46 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
Publications are received periodically from the unit (donor no. 7292 ).
The records are open for research.
The Department of Internal Medicine of the University of Michigan Medical School had its origins in 1848 when Abram Sager was appointed professor of Theory and Practice of Medicine. The department included, at various stages, divisions and studies of pathology, pediatrics and other medical disciplines in the fledgling field of internal medicine. The department was officially given the name of Department of Internal Medicine in 1908.
Dr. Cyrus C. Sturgis was named the first chair of the Department of Internal Medicine in 1928; he served at this post until his retirement in 1959. Sturgis divided the department into four general medical services: medical outpatient service, private medical service, tuberculosis service and a diabetic outpatient service. Over time the department grew and changed to parallel the changes in medical research and science. Dr. William D. Robinson succeeded Dr. Sturgis as chair of the department in 1959. He was replaced by Dr. William N. Kelly in 1971. (Dr. Robinson's personal papers are also located at the Bentley Historical Library.)
Under Dr. Kelly's leadership, the department's budget grew from $2 million to $39 million as he strove to make it one of the leading departments in the country. Divisions were added and restructured as Kelly worked to develop and strengthen clinical research and new multi-disciplinary centers. He also sought to improve interdepartmental cooperation and collaboration. Dr. Kelly left the department in 1990. He was replaced by Dr. Tadataka Yamada, who served until 1996. Yamada was followed by H. David Humes.
As of 1993, 14 divisions comprise the department: Allergy, Cardiology, Endocrinology and Metabolism, Gastroentology, General Medicine, Geriatric Medicine, Hematology and Oncology, Hypertension, Infectious Diseases, Molecular Genetics, Neurology, Nuclear Medicine, Pulmonary, and Rheumatology.
For more information, see the department's web page at: http://www.med.umich.edu/intmed/.
The Department of Internal Medicine Publications contains two series, Unit Publications and Sub-Unit Publications. The Unit Publications series contains printed material published specifically by the Department of Internal Medicine. These publications are defined as being widely distributed and may be published at regular intervals. They are arranged by genre of the publication. The Sub-Unit Publications series contains publications from subordinate offices, departments, programs and organizations within the Department of Internal Medicine. These publications are arranged alphabetically by the creating sub-unit.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Dept. of Internal Medicine.; University of Michigan. Division of Cardiology.; University of Michigan. Molecular Medicine and Genetics Division.; University of Michigan. Division of Nuclear Medicine.; Internal medicine--Study and teaching (Higher)
Contributors:
University of Michigan. Division of Cardiology.; University of Michigan. Molecular Medicine and Genetics Division.; University of Michigan. Division of Nuclear Medicine.
Genre/Form:
Annual reports.; Pamphlets.; Programs.; Regulations.; Newsletters.; Reports.
- Unit Publications
  The Unit Publications series includes annual reports dating from 1975/1976, 1989-1995 and 1999/2000. These annual reports include a report from the department chair as well as descriptions of the various divisions, research, education, and patient services. Containing the same information under a different title, the Annual Progress Report: Executive Summary covers the years 1979/80-1980/81 and 1984/1985-1986/1987. Bibliographies of articles published by the faculty of the Department of Internal Medicine will be found in the folder labeled Reprints--Department of Internal Medicine. There are bibliographies for the years 1973, 1975, 1976 and 1978. There is also a program from the 1948 meeting of the Texas Internists Club. There are two reports, Hospitals Program for Excellence Report and The Management of Exam Rooms, both written in 1995.
  - Announcements (Box 1)
    - New Appointments, 1993 (Box 1)
  - Annual Reports
    - Annual Report, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
    - Annual Report, 1989-1990 (Box 1)
    - Annual Report, 1991-1995, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - Annual Report, 1999-2000 (Box 1)
    - Annual Progress Report: Executive Summary
      - 1979-1981, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - 1984-1987, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Bibliographies
    - Reprints--Department of Internal Medicine, 1968-1978, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Brochures
    - General undated (Box 1)
  - Invitations 1989 (Box 1)
  - Programs
    - Annual Dinner, 1983 (Box 1)
    - The Texas Internists Club Program, 1948 (Box 1)
  - Reports
    - Hospitals Program for Excellence Report, 1995 (Box 1)
    - The Management of Exam Rooms, 1995 (Box 1)
- Sub-Unit Publications
  The Sub-Unit Publications include brochures from the Division of Cardiology dated 1974 though 1982, the Division of Molecular and Human Genetics issued in 1991, and the Division of Nuclear Medicine published in 1988. The Division of General Medicine publications are reports describing the Integrated Inpatient Management Model which were published from 1991 to 1993. The House Officer and Fellowship Training Programs include annual reports dated 1996 and bulletins issued from 1980/1981 and 1990.
  - Division of Cardiology
    - Brochures
      - General 1974-1982 (Box 1)
  - Division of General Medicine
    - Reports
      - Integrated Inpatient Management Model
        - Final Report, 1991 (Box 1)
        - Quarterly Report, 1993 (Box 1)
        - Publications and Abstracts, 1991 (Box 1)
  - Division of Molecular and Human Genetics
    - Brochures
      - General 1991 (Box 1)
  - Division of Nuclear Medicine
    - Brochures
      - General 1988, undated (Box 1)
  - House Officer and Fellowship Training Programs
    - Annual Reports 1996 (Box 1)
    - Bulletins
      - House Officer and Fellowship Training Programs, 1980-1981, 1990 (Box 1)
Related Material
For additional printed works on medical education at the university, the researcher should search the Bentley Library catalogs under the following University of Michigan headings:
Department of Anatomy and Cell Biology
Department of Biological Chemistry
Department of Family Practice
Department of Microbiology and Immunology
Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology
Department of Pathology
Department of Pediatrics
Department of Pharmacology
Department of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation
Department of Physiology
Department of Postgraduate Medicine and Health Professions Education
Department of Psychiatry
Department of Radiology
Department of Surgery
Homeopathic Medical School
Integrated Premedical Medical Program
Medical Scientist Training Program
Medical School
Vice Provost for Medical Affairs